Guide to the Phi Beta Kappa. Beta of North Carolina Chapter (Duke University) Records, 1913-1996
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Phi Beta Kappa. Beta of North Carolina Chapter (Duke University) records 1913-1996
University Archives, Duke University
Phi Beta Kappa. Beta Chapter of North Carolina (Duke University)
5 Linear Feet 5,000 Items
Beta of North Carolina, the Phi Beta Kappa chapter at Duke University, was founded at Trinity College in March, 1920, after ten years of effort by the President and Dean of the College to secure a charter.
The collection includes minute books, correspondence, the original charter, manuals, handbooks, reports, and other related materials. Dates range from 1913-1996.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Phi Beta Kappa. Beta of North Carolina Chapter (Duke University) Records were received by the University Archives as a series of transfers by various sources.
Historical Note
Phi Beta Kappa, the nation's oldest and largest academic honor society, was founded on Dec. 5, 1776, by five students at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg, VA. It was the first society to have a Greek letter name, and in its early years, it introduced the essential characteristics of such societies: an oath of secrecy (discarded in 1831), a badge, mottoes in Latin and Greek, a code of laws, and an elaborate initiation ritual. The members held regular meetings, generally with an emphasis on literary exercises, especially composition and debating. Fraternal sentiments were fostered, and the purpose of some meetings was simply good fellowship.
The original Phi Beta Kappa Society was active for only four years because the approach of the British Army under General Cornwallis forced the college to close. But the faith of those youthful scholars in the future of their Society is shown by their preparation of charters for branches at two other institutions. A charter was voted to Harvard, on Dec. 4, 1779, and to Yale four days later. The charters were delivered-in reverse order-- to groups of students in New Haven, Conn., and in Cambridge, Mass., creating Alpha of Connecticut at Yale in November 1780, and Alpha of Massachusetts at Harvard in September 1781. This began the tradition of designating each state's chapter with a letter from the Greek alphabet to indicate where it fits chronologically in that state's chapters.
The two New England branches preserved the essential qualities of the Virginia experience, adopting changes in procedure to suit local conditions. Shortly before the end of the academic year, the members selected from the junior class a small group of outstanding students who, the following year, constituted the "immediate society." Later this role would be assumed by faculty members who had been invited to join Phi Beta Kappa as undergraduates, and most of a chapter's new members would be initiated as seniors.
In 1988, the delegates at the 35th Triennial Council voted to change the organization's name to "The Phi Beta Kappa Society." This inclusive designation, also the historic name of the Society, now appears on all of its legal documents and publications.
Beta of North Carolina, the Phi Beta Kappa chapter at Duke University, was founded at Trinity College in March, 1920, after ten years of effort by the President and Dean of the College to secure a charter.
Collection Overview
Contains materials which include the paperwork associated with Trinity College's 10 year quest for a Phi Beta Kappa charter as well as minute books, clippings, and membership lists. Additionally, the collection contains the original charter, records concerning the chapter's 75th anniversary, nominations, elections, handbooks, manuals, annual reports and related matters. There are restricted folders within this collection that are marked both on this finding aid and on the folder. Dates range from 1913-1996.
Accessions processed in this finding aid: A2002-9, A2000-25, A95-36, A92-88, A56-726, A56-744, A71-81, A71-402, A72-18, A72-48, A73-110, A74-89, A77-123, A80-65, A80-203, A84-45, and A84-60.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Phi Beta Kappa
Phi Beta Kappa History
Phi Beta Kappa. Beta of North Carolina -- Anniversaries, etc.--1995
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Students
Duke University -- History -- 20th century
Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.
William H. Glasson Papers, 1891-1946, undated
Duke University Archives
Robert S. Rankin Papers, 1898-1977 (bulk 1927-1976)
Duke University Archives
James Cannon Papers, 1912-1974
Duke University Archives
Richard L. Watson Papers, 1941-1989
Duke University Archives
Otto Meier Records and Papers, 1931-1979
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa, Delegates Manual, 27th Triennial Council, 1964 August 30-September 2 (Box 1)
  - United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa, Delegates Manual, 29th Triennial Council, 1970 September 9-11
  - Letters of Acceptance, A-G, 1920-circa 1934
  - Letters of Acceptance with one letter of rejection, H-P, 1920-circa 1934
  - Letters of Acceptance, R-Y, 1920-circa 1934
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Constitution, By-laws, Committees, and Meetings, 1919-1976
  - Application and paperwork for chapter establishment at Trinity College and Treasurer's Reports, 1913-1949
  - Installation of Phi Beta Kappa Chapter at Trinity College, audits, membership lists, clippings, data reports, The Edens Key, and correspondence, 1920-1950
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1971
  - The Founding of the Phi Beta Kappa Chapter at Duke University, Carl Anderson, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Minute Book, 1940-1968
  - Minute Book, 1919-1940
  - Receipts and Expenditures Notebook, 1919-1926
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1966-1977
  - Working file of Undergraduate Elections Committee, A-K, from about 1948-1971 (Box 3)
  - Working file of Undergraduate Elections Committee, L-Z, from about 1948-1971
  - Printed Material: Scholarship, Education, and the Bible, Words and Music, The Middle Course, The Principal Instrument of Freedom, Phi Beta Kappa Gamma of Virginia, An Art and a Science, Science, Life and Landscape, The Carleton Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa, The Academic Environment, The American Scholar's Complex Fate, The Intellectual: Creator and Critic, Wake County Association of Phi Beta Kappa, All Coherence Gone, 1959-1970
  - Elections, Alumni, 1960-1975 (Box 4)
  - Elections, Reports of Undergraduate Committee, 1968-1977
  - Visiting Scholars, 1958-1970
  - Phi Beta Kappa, President Williams' file, 1975-1976
  - Elections, Affirmations, 1971 September-1979
  - Phi Beta Kappa, records, 1961-1982, RESTRICTED
  - Fall Initiates, 2000
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Keys, Mementoes, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa: South Atlantic District, 1960-1963
  - Phi Beta Kappa: W. F. Stinespring, Address before PBK Chapters in NC, 1961-1962
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Secretary Stinespring, Correspondence, 1948-1971
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Annual Reports, 1951-1959
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Annual Reports, 1959-1971
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Elections, Honorary, 1950-1969
  - Elections, Affirmations, Secretary Stinespring, 1971 June
  - Phi Beta Kappa Membership Lists, Undergraduate elections, 1958-1963
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Elections, graduate, 1958-1969, RESTRICTED
  - Phi Beta Kappa Membership List, permanent, 1958-1959
  - Phi Beta Kappa Elections Committee, 1965-1966
  - Phi Beta Kappa Elections Committee, 1966-1967
  - Phi Beta Kappa Elections Committee, Minutes of Committee Reports to Chapter, 1967-1968
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1969-1970
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Committees, 1942-1979
  - Duke University Phi Beta Kappa, 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1965-1966
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1964-1965
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1970-1971
  - Newspaper Publicity, 1959-1971
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1967-1968
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1968-1969
  - Membership Lists, 1961-1962
  - Undergraduate Elections, 1958 October 22
  - Undergraduate Elections, 1959 June 6
  - Chapter Membership Lists, 1966-1970
  - Annual Dinner Meetings, 1959-1979
  - United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa, Delegates Manual, 28th Triennial Council, 1967 August 27-29
  - Treasurer's Report, 1958 October 1-1959 September 30
  - Miscellaneous Chapter Correspondence and Notes, to 1971 June
  - A Ritual of Phi Beta Kappa, Sesquicentennial Edition, 1928
  - Phi Beta Kappa Banquet, 1967 August 28
  - Phi Beta Kappa Distribution Requirements, 1989-1996 (Box 7)
  - The Initiation Ceremony, PBK Beta of North Carolina, 1988
  - The Founding of the Phi Beta Kappa Chapter at Duke University, Carl Anderson, 1987
  - Lecturers, Speakers for Annual Meeting, 1970-1980
  - Forms, Notice of February Meeting, 1969-1980
  - Forms, Initiation by mail, undated
  - Forms, Notice of December meeting, 1971-1980
  - Forms, Notice of April meeting, 1970-1980
  - Forms, Phi Beta Kappa Key Order, 1974-1976
  - Forms, Phi Beta Kappa Membership Cards, undated
  - Lectures, Visiting Lecturers, 1977-1979
  - Lectures, Visiting Scholars, 1972-1980
  - Members, Affiliated, 1971-1980
  - Imposters, 1960-1966
  - Members, Lost, 1972
  - Members, Courtesy initiations, 1974-1978
  - Members, Sign-in sheets, attendance records, 1970
  - Members, Computerized lists of Duke initiates, 1979-1980
  - New Members, by major, 1975-1979
  - Elections, Individual inquiries, 1969-1980, RESTRICTED
  - Elections, Declinations, 1942-1976
  - Elections, Affirmations, 1979-1980
  - Elections, Reports of committee on members in course, 1973-1980
  - Elections, Undergraduate chart, 1967
  - Chapter, By-laws, 1954 July 1
  - Chapter, Superseded by-laws, 1939-1973
  - Chapter, Annual mailing lists, 1970-1972
  - Chapter, Mailing list, 1976-1977
  - Chapter, Mailing List, 1977-1978
  - Chapter, Mailing List, 1978-1979
  - Chapter, Nominating committee, 1972-1979
  - Chapter, Public relations, 1962-1980
  - Chapter Operations, Secretary's functions, 1975-1980
  - Chapter, Standards, 1960-1976
  - Chapter, Ad hoc, Eligibility Standards, 1977-1978
  - Phi Beta Kappa Nomination Committee, 1982
  - Chapter, Mailing list, 1979-1980
  - Phi Beta Kappa, Grad election, 1979-1980, RESTRICTED
  - Phi Beta Kappa, Recommendations, 1978, RESTRICTED
  - Phi Beta Kappa, Recommendations, 1975-1977, RESTRICTED
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1978-1979, RESTRICTED
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1976-1982, RESTRICTED
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1980-1981
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1980-1981
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1979-1980, RESTRICTED
  - PBK, 1974-1977, RESTRICTED
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1977
  - Chapter, Key orders, 1979-1980
  - Chapter, Executive Committee, 1980
  - Chapter, Awards and Prizes, 1979
  - Chapter, Ad hoc, social occasions, 1977-1978
  - United Chapters, Triennial council, 1976
  - United Chapters, Triennial council, 1973
  - United Chapters, Triennial council, 1970
  - United Chapters, Triennial council, 1967
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981
  - Current, Pending business, 1978-1980
  - Current, Senators, 1971-1973
  - Secretary, Miscellaneous correspondence, 1968-1980
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Alumni Elections, 1992-1993 (Box 8)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1989-1994
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1994
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1995-1997
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Alumni Nominations, 1996
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1995
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Alumni Elections, 1993-1994
  - Phi Beta Kappa: Lists, 1992-1995
  - Phi Beta Kappa: 75th Anniversary, 1995
  - Phi Beta Kappa. Beta of North Carolina Charter, 1919, on-site, Drawer 6 (Opaper Drawer 6)